Finding Aid for the Rick Barton Drawings and Paintings LSC.2374
UCLA Library Special Collections
Rick Barton drawings and paintings
circa 1956-1964
UCLA Library Special Collections
Evans, Henry Herman
Barton, Rick
LSC.2374
11.25 linear feet (3 flat boxes, 3 oversize flat boxes, 1 map folder) (775 drawings, 4 paintings)
Rick Barton was a gay Beat artist who lived in San Francisco in the 1950s and 1960s. The collection is primarily comprised of drawings created by Barton, chiefly in pen and ink, in the late 1950s to early 1960s.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Henry Evans, 1971.
Custodial History
Drawings were purchased from the artist by Henry Evans, printmaker and owner of Peregrine Press.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9992725983606533
Biographical History
Rick Barton was born in New York in 1928. He was an artist who claimed to have conducted a self-guided education at the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the New York Public Library. While serving in the U.S. Navy in 1947, he traveled to China where he observed traditional line painting. He was most prolific in the gay San Francisco Beat subculture of the 1950s and 1960s. There he garnered a group of disciples who were drawn to his unique artistic style, which evidences an array of influences, including Chinese line painting, Renaissance woodcut illustrations, and Cubism. Barton drew his surroundings constantly, and was most attracted to subjects such as rooms, people, hands, cafés, churches and botanicals, which were represented in detailed and imagined perspectives. While he primarily lived in San Francisco, Barton spent time in Los Angeles, drawing spaces like Olvera Street, Bunker Hill, and other Los Angeles environs. Some of his drawings were printed by Henry Evans, who ran the Peregrine Press in San Francisco in the 1950s and 1960s, and who supported Barton by purchasing what is now the largest extant collection of his original drawings throughout those years. Barton passed in 1992.
Sources: The Morgan Library & Museum Associate Curator of Modern & Contempory Drawings Rachel Federman and "Rick Barton," The Morgan Library & Museum, accessed October 2019, https://www.themorgan.org/drawings/item/403453.
Scope and Content
Collection is comprised of works of art on paper by artist Rick Barton. The drawings were primarily done in pen and ink, though, at least three of them, drawn in prison, appear to have been drawn in charcoal with burnt wood matches. Many of the drawings were published by the Peregrine Press in the Press's limited edition books and print portfolios.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in chronological order.
Related Materials
Peregrine Press and Henry H. Evans collection (Press coll. Archives Peregrine). Available at UCLA. Clark (William Andrews) Memorial Library.
Peregrine Press; Beats (Persons) -- California -- San Francisco; Evans, Henry Herman; Barton, Rick -- Archives
- Drawings, circa 1958; 6 items (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Drawings, circa 1959; 58 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Drawings, circa 1960; 158 items (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
- Drawings, circa 1961; 221 items (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Drawings, circa 1962; 204 items (Box 2, Folder 5-6, Box 3, Folder 1-4)
- Drawings, undated; 31 items (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Oversize drawings, circa 1958; 8 items (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Oversize drawings, circa 1959; 10 items (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Oversize drawings, circa 1960; 26 items (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
- Oversize drawings, circa 1961; 23 items (Box 4, Folder 5, Box 5, Folder 1)
- Oversize drawings, circa 1962; 24 items (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
- Print, circa 1964; 1 items (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Oversize drawings, undated; 4 items (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Oversize drawing, circa 1961; 1 items (Folder 6)
- Painted by Rick Barton while drunk of Patricia Evans, circa 1956; 1 items 24.5 x 17 cm. (Box 7)
- Portrait of Nancy Larson, circa September 1958; 1 items (Box 7)
- "Portrait of man with beard", circa September 1958; 1 items (Box 7)
- "Abstract painting with figure", undated; 1 items (Box 7)